Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 13 -- Miscellaneous Franklin Materials 1640-1791 Mss.B.F85inventory13
American Philosophical Society
- Miscellaneous Franklin Materials
  - Miscellaneous Papers., 1766 February 11; D. 1p.; The Court for Northampton County, Pennsylvania
    Unanimous opinion that the Stamp Act is unconstitutional, and doe not bind the officers or affect the Colony.
  - to Mrs. Deborah Franklin, Philadelphia., 1766 February 15; A.L.S. 6p.; Holt, John. New York
    Will send a few bushels of apples, if desired. Extract of a letter from Dr. Franklin to Mr. [John] Hughes he published in the newspaper of October 10, 1765. The commotion in New York over the purchase of stamped paper. Wishes Mrs. Franklin would try to persuade Mr.[John] Hughes to make absolute renunciation of the Stamp office, as the Stamp Act will never go into effect in America.
  - to Hon. Thomas Gage., 1766 March 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Baynton, Wharton and Morgan. Philadelphia
    Received a letter from Capt. [Robert] Callender, the contents of which have greatly distressed them, as their property is again in jeopardy and a base confederacy formed to hinder them from prosecuting their rade with the natives; assure him that they dare not move their property either to or from Fort Pitt unless he is pleased to give them an escort, and lodge a party of men in Justice [William] Smith's neighborhood.
  - to Messrs. Baynton, Wharton and Morgan., 1766 March 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Callender, Robert. Lancaster
    Notwithstanding the Black boys' promise not to attack the goods, it will not be safe to move them without an escort as far as Bedford. Goods lying in Conegocheague may be safe, but will not move any of them until he hears from them.
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin. Philadelphia., 1766 April 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Smith, Robert. Philadelphia
    Relative to the indebtedness of Barnabas Neaves, one of her tenants.
  - to John Hall., 1766 April 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Clarkson, Matthew and Michael Hillegas. Philadelphia
    Location of a tract of land they are interested in. Requests him a survey and make observations on the situation, appearance and quality of the land, and to observe a spot fit for a town either on Vashademoick or St. John's River.
  - to William Franklin, 1766 April 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Galloway, Joseph
    Repeal of the Stamp Act. Dr. [John] Fothergill's and Mr. [George] Whitefield's account of Dr. Franklin's examination before the House of Commons. Emblematical representation of Great Britain dismembered.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 311).
  - Miscellaneous Papers., 1766 May 3; D. 1p.; Sir Henry Moore, Governor of New York
    Commission of James Parker as Land-Waiter of the Port of New York.
  - Miscellaneous Papers., 1766 June 6; D. 1p.; The Assembly of Pennsylvania
    Resolutions relative to aids to be granted to the Crown. Attested by Cha[rle]s Moore, Clerk.
  - to Mrs. Deborah Franklin, Philadelphia., 1766 August 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Hussey, Christopher. Nantucket
    Solicits her care of his son, Albert, who is sent to Philadelphia to have the small-pox by inoculation.
  - to Deborah Franklin, Philadelphia., 1766 September 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Folger, Timothy. Nantucket
    Sends a bundle of codfish.
  - to William Franklin., 1766 September 1; A.L.S. 2p.; James, Abel. Philadelphia
    Correction of a bill. Will meet Friend Worsam at the dock, with the carriage. Local politics. Family affairs.
  - to William Franklin., 1766 September 13; A.L.S. 11.; Galloway, Joseph
    Asks advice as to publishing an article to show that he had been a uniform supporter of the repeal of the Stamp Act.
  - to William Franklin., 1766 October 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Davenport, Josiah Franklin. Burlington
    News of the election. Remarks of Luke Morris and Captain Haselton.
  - to William Franklin., 1766 October 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Davenport, Josiah Franklin
    Account of election disputes.
  - to [Mrs. Deborah Franklin], Philadelphia., 1766 November 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Parker, James. New york
    Would be glad to receive a Bake-stone from Philadelphia, as none can be obtained in New York.
  - to Mrs. Deborah Franklin., 1766 December 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Hussey, Christopher. Nantucket
    His son, Albert, just arrived from Philadelphia. Is grateful for the good care he received while there. Will send payment by Captain Starbuck.
  - to William Franklin, Burlington., 1766 December 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Evans, Cadwalader. Philadelphia
    Sends a packet received from Mr. [Joseph] Galloway. Political affairs. Dr. Franklin in London.
  - to [Mrs. Deborah Franklin]., 1766 December 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Parker, James. New york
    Has not money enough to buy wood or meat. His newspaper [The New York Gazette] is a failure and his credit is low. Does not like Gilbert Tennent; thinks him a fortune-hunter.
  - to William Franklin., 1766 December 10; L.S. 3p.; Baynton, Wharton and Morgan. Burlington. N.J
    Request him to secure the aid of his father in procuring a loan for them to assist in carrying on the peltry and fur trade.
  - to Mrs. Deborah Franklin, Philadelphia., 1766 December 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Parker, James. New york
    His son got home; his health recovered. Wants one of Dr. Franklin's sliding irons for his fire place. Will remit the first money he gets.
  - to W[illiam] Franklin, Burlington., 1766 December 17; A.L.S. 1P.; Galloway, Joseph
    Has had to condemn the conduct of Abel James. He has lost all credit with his friends.
  - to [Chief Justice] William Hey., 1766 December 19; L.S. 2p.; Finlay, Hugh. Quebec Post Office
    Continual complaints from postmen; would like to be informed when he may expect a reply to his petition concerning the regulation of the public post, that he may inform the people. Mr. Finlay's plan for delivering and collecting mail; the public complain that there is no way of carrying on a correspondence with the parishes on the River Sorrel, and states that his complaint would be removed by his plan.
  - to [William Franklin]., 1766 December 21; A.L. 2p.; Galloway, Joseph. Philadelphia
    Has had a letter from Dr. Franklin concerning the change of the Ministry, and he has sent him a Plan for a General Currency it America, and his humorous petition relative to the Act for sending felons to America.
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin., 1766 December 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Parker, James. New york
    Encloses £7 5 s. Has not been able to obtain any more. His family go in rags.
  - to William Franklin., 1766 December 27; A.L.S. 4p.; Wharton, Samuel. New York
    Indian losses. Grant of land. Conversation with General Gags Grossip from London in regard to Dr. Franklin.
  - to William Franklin, Burlington., 1766 December ?; A.L.S. 3p.; Wharton, Samuel. New York
    Paper currency about to be established in New York. Dr. McLean [Lauchlan Maclane], who formerly lived in Philadelphia, appointed one of the under-secretaries to Lord Shelburne.
  - to Governor Franklin., A.L. 4p.; -----, -----
    Acknowledging the extracts quoted from Dr. Franklin's last letter showing his interest in the two projects, the settlement at the Illinois and restitution for the Indian losses. Intends writing to Sir William Johnson regarding this matter. Doctor L[auchlan] Maclane appointed Secretary to Lord Shelburne.
    (Incomplete.)
  - to William Franklin., 1767 February 10; A.L.S. 4p.; Evans, Cadwalader. Philadelphia
    Prescription for Mrs. [Elizabeth] Franklin. Pennsylvania politics. Clash over the circuit bill. The Assembly still sitting, and when employed about merely private bills the majority was oftenest on the side of a certain Chief Justice [William Allen], and he often felicitated himself on the harmony that subsisted, but when supplies came to be considered and officers to be named in bills he appeared the same greasy, vociferous, gormandising giant he ever was, and as great a majority as ever coalesced and were as firm as G[eorge] Ashbridge against him. It is asserted that Alison, Ewing and several of that sort have had two or three meetings to consult what was to be done on behalf of Bradford and their ultimate resolution that he had better disregard whatever was said of him by ye lover of Justice and treat it with silent contempt. Mr. James sends a collar of Brawn to Mrs. Franklin.
  - to James Potts, Clerk of the Council., 1767 February 20; L. 1p.; Finlay, Hugh. Quebec Post Office
    Petitioned the Governor and Council to strengthen the power vested in him that he may meet no difficulty in regulating the postmen; annexed a plan to his petition; has not received a copy of the reply from the Committee to whom it was referred.
  - to William Franklin, Burlington., 1767 February 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Galloway, Joseph. Philadelphia
    Failure of the Governor of Pennsylvania to pass the circuit bill. The transaction explained in Goddard's paper. Letters from Dr. Franklin.
  - to James Goldfrap, Secretary to the Province of Quebec., 1767 February 21; L.S. 2p.; Finlay, Hugh. Quebec Post Office
    Necessary to inform the Postmasters-General, immediately, of the reasons why he cannot obey their orders; begs him to lay General Carleton's commands on him in writing. Mr. [William] Hey, the Chief Justice, informed him that the Governor and Council did not choose to give any orders concerning the posts; the Acts of Parliament in force; his instructions from the Postmasters-General and an ordinance passed in the Province were very good rules for him to walk by. Begs to have His Excellency's commands in writing, that he may account to his superiors.
  - to Hugh Finlay., 1767 February 22; L.S. 1p.; Goldfrap, James. Quebec
    His advertisements in the Quebec Gazette disapproved of by the Lieutenant-Governor, who was a good deal surprised that he should urge him to give his message in writing; that he doubts his being warrented by orders from the Postmasters-General to assume a legislative style, and desires to know why they were not communicated to the Government. Commands him to bring the said orders to him in Council tomorrow.
  - to Samuel Rhoads, Philadelphia., 1767 March 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Smith, Robert. Philadelphia
    Asks if he could put him in a way of getting £50 or £60 on account of Benjamin Franklin; is in great need of money and is uncertain when Mr. Franklin will return. Has received £446 at various times, and Mr. Franklin lent him £200 before there was so much due. According to his estimates he may need £780 for materials for his house.
  - to The Mayor's Court., 1767 April 7, July 7, October 27; D.S. 8p.; Petitions of Josiah Franklin Davenport. Philadelphia
    To be allowed to keep a Public House. First petition signed by 81 residents of Philadelphia, the second by 196 residents, the third by none. All three petitions were rejected.
  - to Mrs. Deborah Franklin, Philadelphia., 1767 May 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Parker, James. New york
    Sends a psalm book and the money for the Franklin. Is only agent for Mr. Smith's Burlington History1 but will send one if desired.
    1 "History of the Colony of Nova Caesaria, or New Jersey, by Samuel Smith," printed at Burlington by James Parker.
  - to William Franklin., 1767 May 16; A.L.S. 1p.; James, Abel. Philadelphia
    Relative to the affairs of Tench Francis.
  - to Lord Chatham., 1767 January 30; L.S. 2p.; Ferdinand of Brunswick, Prince
    Has been informed that Lord Clive in on his return from India and that in a little time he will have a successor in the command of the troops. Recommends Major-General [John] Beckwith, a man of a open, incorruptible, just and humane character, as Lord Clive's successor. General Beckwith as a military leader.
    (Copy and translation.)
  - to John Hall, Philadelphia., 1767 August 16; A.L.S. 1P.; Peabody, Francis. Halifax
    Governor and Council have voted the stream to Col. Glazier, Capt. Gould, Mr. [John] Hall and himself, and also gave them two thousand acres of land for an encouragement for building and carrying on their iron works; the stream better than he expected for situation and bigness. Success of grain raising. Sorry he did not come over, as they want him for Justice of the Peace. Death of Mr. Burpy.
  - to Mrs. Deborah Franklin, Philadelphia., 1767 August 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Parker, James. New york
    Sorry for the failure in the matter of sending the lobsters; pains and money he expended; could not procure suitable pots; claim of the woman who makes them that Franklin owes her for a pot made for him when he first went to London.
  - to William Franklin., 1767 September 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Galloway, Joseph. Burlington
    Relative to the financial affairs of B[aynton], W[harton] and M[organ]. S[amuel] W[harton] may be sent to the Indian country, though sorely needed to manage his business at home, with Sir W[illiam] J[ohnson] and Mr.[George] C[roghan].
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1767 September 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Peyton, John. London
    Had a fine passage of only five weeks, and made Dr. Franklin and Mrs. [Margaret] Stevenson happy with her favors. Sends his compliments to Mr. [Richard] Bache [upon his marriage].
  - to [Mrs. Deborah Franklin], Philadelphia., 1767 September 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, William. Burlington
    The packet from his father had enclosed a letter for her. His father had not then heard of Mr. [Richard] Bache's misfortune. He acquaints him that he has left his consent to Sally [Franklin]'s marriage entirely to his wife.
  - to James West of Alscot., 1767 October 21; D.S. 2p.; David Hall of Lewes, Delaware. England
    Power of attorney.
  - to John Hall., 1767 October 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Morris, Charles Jr. Halifax Penna
    The Governor will grant the land adjoining Maugerville, where there is a fine stream of water and plenty of iron ore, to Capt. [Francis] Peabody, Col. Glazier. Mr. Gould (Private Secretary to the Governor) and Mr. [John] Hall, on condition that they erect a bloomary. Proposes to give all the unoccupied land to industrious persons or certain conditions.
  - Miscellaneous Papers., 1767 October 17; L.S. 1p.; Leboistel, Lt.-Col. -----. Strasbourg
    Official recommendation of Paul François Jean Baptiste de Carantene.
  - to Rev. Dr. [Francis] Alison, Philadelphia., 1767 October 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Eagleson, Jno. Halifax Penna
    Should those who are proprietors, and incline to settle townships, exert themselves, they must in a few years reap the advantage. Either by not considering their difficulties or being unwilling to be at what they think a too great expense in enabling them to subsist for some time, they run the risk of losing all or hurting the settlement of the Colony. An instance of that sort which occurred to settlers destined for Potitwodiac, the property of Dr. [William] Smith and Co.
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1767 November 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Bache, Theophylact. New York
    Mr. and Mrs. Richard Bache to return home as soon as their friends permit. Has sent Mrs. Franklin a box of lobsters and a barrel of nuts.
  - to William Franklin., 1768 January 25; A.L. 4p. A.L. 4p. A.L. 4p. A.L. 4p.; Evans, Cadwalader. Philadelphia
    The old difference between Dr. [John] Morgan and Dr. [William] Shippen. The former began to form a Medical Society and invited all the faculty to join except both the Shippens. He and some others did not acquiesce as they thought it would imply that the Shippens were unfit to be members and might be a real injury to them. Dr. [Thomas] Bond then endeavored to revive the [American Philosophical] Society. He broached the scheme to several and a plan was fixed and they held a meeting, at which were present Dr. Bond, the two Shippens, [William] Smith, [Francis] Alison, [John] Ewing, and Sam[uel] R[h]oads, at Byrnes's to elect a President and other officers. Was told that Dr. Franklin was to be President and Smith or Ewing Secretary, and they balloted in Governor [John] Penn and between twenty or thirty others. He was not there because he did not like the company. Some of the members of the young Junto1 have met every Friday night for two or three years past. All the Trustees of the College [of Philadelphia] are included in the twenty five or thirty balloted in by Dr. Bond, but he is persuaded that they desire to avail themselves of their assistance to increase the reputation of the College. He would rather stand alone than join them, because it is preposterous to associate in philosophical disquisitions, which require the utmost precision and veracity, with [William] Smith, [Francis] Alison, [John] Ewing, and [Hugh] Williamson, whom they know have stuck at no lies to injure them. The Assembly is puzzled what to do with the Dutchman who killed the Indians below Shamokin. The young Junto, ever since last September, have been fabricating a plan to forward their design and several of our friends are disposed in favor it, but Edmund Physic[k], a proprietary officer, and some other of the company are rather for junction.
    (Incomplete and mutilated.)
    1 [The American Society held at Philadelphia for Promoting Useful Knowledge.]
  - to Cadwalader Evans., 1768 January 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, William
    Is obliged for the account of the two new [American] Philosophical Societies; but the printed proposals, to which he was referred, were not sent. Is at a loss to know with what propriety they can talk of reviving the old Society begun by his father. The papers, etc., were, and he thinks are now, in possession of his father. Thinks they should have summoned a meeting of all the old members and consulted them. Questions whether any of the persons who met to revive it were ever members, except Dr. [Thomas] Bond and [Samuel] Rhoads. Thinks their scheme of calling this a revival of the old [American Philosophical] Society is to induce his father to countenance it or, by using his name, to engage his old friends and connections to join them, The bait won't take with him, and he is glad it has not with Dr. Evans.
  - Miscellaneous Papers., 1768 January and February; 1772 July 9 and November 19; 1773 March 4, 11, 18, 25, and April 1; 5p.; List of Papers Read at the Royal Society
    Memorandum.
  - to Mrs. Benjamin Franklin, Philadelphia., 1768 February 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Hunter, William. Poquoson
    Asks that a Latin grammar may be sent him; may be got at the College. [of Philadelphia.]
  - to [William] Cummings., 1768 February 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Rice, John
    Informed by friends that there are opportunities in America for those capable of instructing in the English language. Has many reasons for wishing to be employed there. Begs him to converse with Dr. Franklin on this subject.
  - to The Printer of the London Chronicle., 1768 March 10; A.L.S. 6p.; A Portugal Merchant. Lisbon
    Resents the charges made by F. + S. that the American people were forbidden the advantage of a direct importation of wine, oil and fruit, from Portugal, but must first take them to England, and thus cost them 30 per cent. more than oterwise, merely that a few Portugal merchants in London may gain a commission on goods going through their hands. Claims that this is due to an Act passed by the British Parliament forbidding them to send any fruit, oil or figs to the Colonies without first being unloaded in England. Sentiments of the Portugal merchants concerning the above Acts of Parliament.
  - to The Commissioners of the Customs at Boston., 1768 March 29 - 1769 April 10; 4p.; Franklin, William, 1731-1813
    Extracts from seven letters relative to complaints of Mrs. [John] Hatton, Collector [of the Customs] at Salem, New Jersey, against the officers of the Province.
  - Miscellaneous Papers., 1768 July 14; D. 4p.; The Privy Council of New Jersey. Burlington
    Charges of misconduct by John Hatton, Collector of His Majesty's Customs, at Salem, against Grant Gibbon, Robert Johnson, Preston Carpenter, and George Trenchard, Justices of the Peace, of Salem Country, and Edward Test, Sheriff, found to be unsubstantiated.
  - to Jane Mecom(e), Boston., 1768 August 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Coffin, Keziah. Nantucket
    News that their vessel is lost is confirmed. Asks her to write to her brother, Benjamin Franklin, on behalf of Cousin [Timothy] Folger, that, by his influence, he may obtain any commission he shall ask for.
  - Miscellaneous Papers., 1768 September 6; Copy of D. 2p.; Anthony Todd, Secretary. General Post Office, London
    Public notice concerning mails.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1768 December 10; D. 1p.; Franklin, Deborah Read Rogers, 1708-1774
    Receipt, as attorney for Benjamin Franklin, for three bonds from Sarah Dewey, executrix of William Mangridge.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1768 December 24; D. 1p.; The Commons House of Assembly of Georgia
    That an address be presented to the King, setting forth the burdens caused by the late Acts of Parliament.
    Attested by John Simpson, Clerk.
  - to The King., 1768 December 24; D.S. N[oble] W[imberly] Jones, Speaker. 2p.; Address from the Commons House of Assembly of Georgia
    Relative to the grievous revenue Acts of Parliament.
  - to American Affairs from about., 1768 to 1773; Diss. 12p.; Narrative of Facts Relative
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1769 February 6 and March 10; D. 3p.; The Merchants of Philadelphia
    Resolutions against the importation of certain articles, until the repeal of the Revenue Acts.
  - to Governor Francis Bernard., 1769 February 16; L. 3p.; The Selectmen of Boston. Boston
    Relative to the uncertain state of public affairs, and to the presence of troops in Boston. Accompanied by the reply of the Governor, dated February 18.
  - to James Balfour [Edinburgh]., 1769 March 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Parker, James. New york
    Has been in a sick bed for the past two months. Will send him the money he sold the remaining books for; impossibility of getting from [John] Holt what he owes for them. Thinks he (Parker) deserves pity more than blame.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1769 March 6; D. 1p.; Order in Council
    To obtain His Majesty's permission to pass a law for making slaves personal estate.
  - to [Mrs. Deborah Franklin], 1769 March 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Parker, James. New york
    His financial and physical troubles. Has sent a bushel and a half of nuts to Franklin.
  - to W[illiam] F[ranklin]., 1769 April 6; L. 2p.; Temple, John. Boston
    Relative to the complaints of Mr. [John] Hatton. Postscript referring to the charges of the Commissioners of Customs against the Post Office and packet boats of America, and Dr. Franklin's report thereon.
  - to A Committee of Merchants of London., 1769 April 8; L.S. Daniel Benezet, et al. 4p.; The Merchants of Philadelphia. Philadelphia
    Memorial against Great Britain's revenue policy.
  - to James Parker., 1769 May 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Monier, Jno. Albany
    Sends him a key for the mails form Albany to New York; safety of the mails from Albany to Canada.
  - to Mrs. Deborah Franklin, Philadelphia., 1769 May 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Parker, James. New york
    Has not heard from Dr. Franklin for a great while. Is well but still weak.
  - to William Franklin., 1769 June 11; L. 1p.; Hughes, John. Walnut Grove
    Expresses thanks for congratulations of Dr. Franklin and his son on something done in his favor. Reflections on resentments in which he was deeply concerned. Will always be loyal to his King.
  - to [Mrs. Deborah Franklin]., 1769 July 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Folger, Timothy. Nantucket
    Sends a bundle of fish, by Captain Joshua Bunker. Saw Dr. Franklin at London frequently during the last winter.
  - to Mrs. [Margaret] Stevenson, London., 1769 August 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Payne, James. Brackley
    Financial distress of Mrs. [Hannah] Walker's family. Thanks Dr. Franklin for paying to his order £5 for Walker's bread. Asks her to request Dr. Franklin for some small annual bounty for Mrs. Walker.
  - to Mrs. Deborah Franklin. Philadelphia., 1769 September 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Mecom, Mrs. Jane. Boston
    Is about to set out for Philadelphia.